A Finding Aid to the Hughie Lee-Smith Papers, circa 1890-2007, bulk 1931-1999, in the Archives of American Art AAA.leeshugh
Archives of American Art
- Interviews, 1973-1998; Series 11; 2.1 Linear feet Box 26-28
  - Interview Regarding 50-Year Retrospective, New Jersey State Museum, 1988 December 12; 1 Sound cassettes Includes transcript. (Box 27, Folder 7-8)
  - Telephone Interview with Dr. L. Reid and Teachers from Pensacola, Florida, 1994 July 8; 1 Sound cassettes Includes trancript. (Box 27, Folder 9-10)
  - Interview with Margot Mifflin, 1994 Summer; 1 Sound cassettes Includes transcript. (Box 27, Folder 11-12)
  - Interview with Luisa Chapman, Hartford Atheneum, 1995 February 20; 1 Sound cassettes Includes transcript. (Box 27, Folder 13-14)
  - Interview with Bethuel Hunter, 1995 June 14; 1 Sound cassettes Includes transcript. (Box 27, Folder 15-16)
  - Interview with Michael Brenson, 1995 July 5; 2 Sound cassettes Includes transcript. (Box 27, Folder 17-18)
  - Interview with National Public Radio, "Alone in the Crowd", 1996 March 28; 1 Sound cassettes (microcassette) Includes transcript.; 2 Sound cassettes Includes transcript. (Box 27, Folder 19-20)
  - Art Evening at the Lotos Club, Honoring Hughie Lee-Smith, 1996 April 23; 2 Sound cassettes Includes transcript. (Box 27, Folder 21-22)
  - Oral History with Lee-Smith, Mother, Daughter, Granddaughter, circa 1976; 1 Sound cassettes Includes transcript. (Box 27, Folder 23-24)
    Cassette and transcript also includes discussion of method and material for painting class, questionnaire for member of curatorial council of SMH, and Lee-Smith reading on the influences of Giorgio di Chirico.
  - Oral History: "Conversation with My Mother"; Informal Chatting with Carol Anderson, 1970s; 1 Sound cassettes Includes transcript. (Box 27, Folder 25-26)
  - Discussion between Hughie, Rex Goreleigh, and Larry Hilton in Rex's Studio; Talk at Western Michigan College, 1970s; 1 Sound cassettes Includes transcript. (Box 27, Folder 27-28)
  - Telephone Interview with Ed Bumgardener, 1977 February 5; 1 Sound cassettes Includes transcript. (Box 27, Folder 29-30)
  - Hughie and Patricia Lee-Smith Discuss Roy Lichtenstein and Artis Lane, 1997; 1 Sound cassettes Includes transcript. (Box 27, Folder 31-32)
  - Conversation with Wife Patricia, 1978 or 1979; 1 Sound cassettes Includes transcript. (Box 27, Folder 33-34)
  - Dinner Conversation with Rex Goreleigh, Hughie and Patricia Lee-Smith, 1985 October 13; 1 Sound cassettes Includes transcript. (Box 28, Folder 1-2)
  - Hughie Lee-Smith "Visit with Titter (my mother) and Tina (my daughter) in Cleveland", 1970s; Transcript only. (Box 28, Folder 3)
  - Hughie Lee-Smith Visit with Christina and Piera, 1978 Fall; Transcript only. (Box 28, Folder 4)
  - Interview with Mike Culter, Ogunquit Museum, 1997 February 7; 2 Sound cassettes Includes transcript. (Box 28, Folder 5-6)
  - Hughie Lee-Smith Speaks on Origins of His Art in Childhood and in Preparation for Artists Fellowship Honor, 1996 May; 1 Sound cassettes Includes transcript. (Box 28, Folder 7-8)
  - Hughie Lee-Smith Talking About 1943 Racism Experiences in Detroit, 1995 August 9; Transcript only. (Box 28, Folder 9)
  - Hughie Lee-Smith Interview, 1998 January 29; 1 Sound cassettes (Box 28, Folder 10)
  - "Patricia - Thoughts and Feelings", 1994 May; 1 Sound cassettes (Box 28, Folder 11)
  - Hughie Lee-Smith Regarding June Kelly Gallery, 1994 July 14; 1 Sound cassettes (Box 28, Folder 12)
  - Proposal for Grant; WPA, undated; 1 Sound cassettes (Box 28, Folder 13)
  - Interview with Karl Fortess, 1973 February 14; 1 Sound cassettes Duplicate copy of sound tape reel; 1 sound tape reels Original; 1 Sound discs (CD) Duplicate copy of sound tape reel (Box 28, Folder 14)
  - Interview for NJN "State of the Arts", 1988 December 7; 1 Videocassettes (BetacamSP); 2 Videocassettes (VHS) Two duplicate VHS recordings of the Betacam SP videocassette. (Box 28, Folder 15)
  - "Hughie Lee-Smith, A Biography of An African American Artist and Educator", 1994 June 6; 1 Videocassettes (VHS) (Box 28, Folder 16)
  - Artists Fellowship Award Ceremony Acceptance Speech, 1996 May; 1 Videocassettes (VHS) (Box 28, Folder 17)
  - "Black Artist in America - Part One and Two by Oakley Holmes Jr.", undated; 1 Videocassettes (VHS) (Box 28, Folder 18)
  - Notes on Transcripts, 1996-1997 (Box 28, Folder 19)
- Documentary Film Materials, 1985-2004; Series 12; 3.5 Linear feet Box 28-32
  Found here are planning documents, research material, and video footage for a documentary about the life and work of Hughie Lee-Smith, produced by New Deal Films, Inc. The documentary was never completed, and all material was returned to Patricia Lee-Smith in 2004. Recordings consist of three sample reel videocassettes as well as 24 master videocassettes (and various duplicate videocassettes) containing footage recorded by New Deal Films for the documentary. Footage includes interviews with artists and art historians, gallery events, and images of Lee-Smith's paintings. A few interviews were also recorded on sound cassette. Researchers should note that one file of audiotape transcripts included in this series are copies of transcripts found in Series 12: Interviews, and not transcripts of interviews conducted for this documentary.
  Research and planning files are arranged before recordings. Master recordings are filed with the duplicate copies.
  - Articles and Clippings, circa 1988-2004 (Box 28, Folder 20-21)
  - Audiotape Transcripts, 1985-1995 (Box 29, Folder 1)
  - Saul Horowitz Correspondence, 2003 (Box 29, Folder 2)
  - Funding, 2001-2005 (Box 29, Folder 3)
  - Hughie Lee-Smith Resumes, 1990s-2004 (Box 29, Folder 4)
  - Photocopies from Archives of Cleveland Institute of Art, 2004 (Box 29, Folder 5)
  - Prints from Ellen Sragow, 2001 (Box 29, Folder 6)
  - Proposal for a Documentary on Hughie Lee-Smith, 2000 (Box 29, Folder 7)
  - Research, Miscellaneous Collections, 2000-2004 (Box 29, Folder 8)
  - "Community Bridges: African American Art Children's Workshop", 1996; 1 Videocassettes (VHS) (Box 29, Folder 9)
  - "Hughie Lee-Smith" Preliminary Sample Reel, 2001 August 27; 1 Videocassettes (BetacamSP) (Box 29, Folder 10)
  - Sample Reels for a Documentary on Hughie Lee-Smith, 2004 August; 2 Videocassettes (VHS) (Box 29, Folder 11)
  - Tape 1 - Artwork, Patricia Lee-Smith Collection, 2000 December 12; 1 Videocassettes (BetacamSP) Duplicate of DVCAM; 1 Videocassettes (DVCAM) Original; 1 Videocassettes (VHS) Duplicate of DVCAM (Box 29, Folder 12-13)
  - Tape 2 - Ruth Creighton Campbell, 2000 December 13; 1 Videocassettes (VHS) Duplicate of DVCAM; 1 Videocassettes (DVCAM) Original; 1 Videocassettes (BetacamSP) (Box 29, Folder 14-15)
  - Tape 3 - Ruth Creighton Campbell; Reginald Gammon, 2000 December 13; 1 Videocassettes (DVCAM) Original; 1 Videocassettes (BetacamSP) Duplicate of DVCAM; 1 Videocassettes (VHS) Duplicate of DVCAM (Box 30, Folder 1-2)
  - Tape 4 - Reginald Gammon, 2000 December 13; 1 Videocassettes (BetacamSP) Duplicate of DVCAM; 1 Videocassettes (VHS) Duplicate of DVCAM; 1 Videocassettes (DVCAM) Original (Box 30, Folder 3-4)
  - Tape 5 - Barbara Fleischman; Art Students League, 2001 January 8; 1 Videocassettes (BetacamSP) Duplicate of DVCAM; 1 Videocassettes (DVCAM) Original; 1 Videocassettes (VHS) Duplicate of DVCAM; Contains both Tape 5 and 6; 1 Sound cassettes Duplicate audio of DVCAM (Box 30, Folder 5)
  - Tape 6 - Lowery Stokes Sims, 2001 January 8; 1 Videocassettes (VHS) Duplicate of DVCAM; Contains both Tape 5 and 6; 1 Videocassettes (BetacamSP) Duplicate of DVCAM; 1 Videocassettes (DVCAM) Original (Box 30, Folder 6)
  - Tape 7 - Kinshasha Council, 2001 January 9; 1 Videocassettes (DVCAM) Original; 1 Videocassettes (VHS) Duplicate of DVCAM. Contains both Tape 7 and 8; 1 Videocassettes (BetacamSP) Duplicate of DVCAM; 1 Sound cassettes Duplicate audio of DVCAM (Box 30, Folder 7)
  - Tape 8 - June Kelly Galleries, circa 2001; 1 Videocassettes (DVCAM) Original; 1 Videocassettes (VHS) Duplicate of DVCAM. Contains both Tape 7 and 8; 1 Videocassettes (BetacamSP) Duplicate of DVCAM (Box 30, Folder 8)
  - Tape 9 - Mark Freeman, 2001 January 9; 1 Videocassettes (DVCAM) Original; 1 Videocassettes (VHS) Duplicate of DVCAM. Contains both Tape 9 and 10; 1 Videocassettes (BetacamSP) Duplicate of DVCAM; 1 Sound cassettes Duplicate audio of DVCAM (Box 30, Folder 9)
  - Tape 10 - Mark Freeman; Will Barnet, 2001 January 9; 1 Videocassettes (VHS) Duplicate of DVCAM. Contains both Tape 9 and 10; 1 Sound cassettes Duplicate audio of DVCAM; 1 Videocassettes (DVCAM) Original; 1 Videocassettes (BetacamSP) Duplicate of DVCAM (Box 31, Folder 1-2)
  - Tapes 11 and 12 - Ernest Crichlow, circa 2001; 1 Sound cassettes Duplicate of DVCAM. Contains both Tape 11 and 12; 2 Videocassettes (BetacamSP) Duplicates of DVCAM; 2 Videocassettes (DVCAM) Originals. Label on Tape 11 also notes "B-Roll. Natl. Academy Ext."; 1 Videocassettes (VHS) Duplicate of DVCAM. Contains both Tape 11 and 12 (Box 31, Folder 3-5)
  - Tape 13 - Ernest Crichlow, circa 2001; 1 Videocassettes (DVCAM) Original; 1 Videocassettes (VHS) Duplicate of DVCAM. Contains both Tapes 13 and 14; 1 Videocassettes (BetacamSP) Duplicate of DVCAM (Box 31, Folder 6)
  - Tape 14 - Ernest Crichlow; Ruth Jett, circa 2001; 1 Videocassettes (VHS) Duplicate of DVCAM. Contains both Tape 13 and 14; 1 Sound cassettes Duplicate audio of DVCAM: Ruth Jett interview; 1 Videocassettes (BetacamSP) Duplicate of DVCAM; 1 Videocassettes (DVCAM) Original (Box 31, Folder 7)
  - Tape 15 - Sara Marion, 2001 March 21; 1 Videocassettes (DVCAM) Original; 1 Videocassettes (BetacamSP) Duplicate of DVCAM; 1 Videocassettes (VHS) Duplicate of DVCAM. Contains both Tape 15 and 16 (Box 31, Folder 8)
  - Tape 16 - Sara Marion; Sharon F. Patton, 2001 March 21; 1 Videocassettes (DVCAM) Original; 1 Videocassettes (BetacamSP) Duplicate of DVCAM; 1 Videocassettes (VHS) Duplicate of DVCAM. Contains both Tape 15 and 16 (Box 31, Folder 9)
  - Tape 17 - Sharon F. Patton; Paintings at UNM, 2001 March 21; 1 Videocassettes (DVCAM) Original; 1 Videocassettes (BetacamSP) Duplicate of DVCAM; 1 Videocassettes (VHS) Duplicate of DVCAM. Contains both Tape 17 and 18 (Box 31, Folder 10)
  - Tape 18 - Paintings and Drawings at UNM, 2001 March 21; 1 Videocassettes (BetacamSP) Duplicate of DVCAM; 1 Videocassettes (DVCAM) Original; 1 Videocassettes (VHS) Duplicate of DVCAM. Contains both Tape 17 and 18 (Box 31, Folder 11)
  - Tape 19 - Artwork, Paintings and Drawings, 2001 June 18; 1 Videocassettes (DVCAM) Original (Box 31, Folder 12)
  - Tape 20 and 21 - Still Photos shot by Tom Zanner, 2004 March 4; 2 Videocassettes (BetacamSP) Duplicates of DVCAM; 2 Videocassettes (DVCAM) Originals (Box 32, Folder 1-2)
  - Tape 22 - Photos and Clippings; Lee-Smith Collection, 2004 March 4; 1 Videocassettes (DVCAM) Original (Box 32, Folder 3)
  - Tape 23 - Stills, 2004 March 17; 1 Videocassettes (DVCAM) Original (Box 32, Folder 4)
  - Tape 24 - Paintings; Patricial Lee-Smith Collection, 2004 August 25; 1 Videocassettes (DVCAM) Original (Box 32, Folder 5)
- Rex Goreleigh Papers, 1935-1994; Series 13; 0.9 Linear feet Box 32-33, 36
  The papers of Rex Goreleigh primarily document his later life and include scattered letters, cards, biographical documents, teaching and financial records, and printed material. Also found are photographs and slides depicting Goreleigh, his studio, and artwork. Goreleigh (1902-1986) was an African American painter who primarily worked in Princeton, New Jersey. He founded his own art school, Studio-on-the-Canal, which was open from 1955 through the 1970s. Goreleigh died in an apartment fire and the papers found here were recovered from his home after his death. Hughie Lee-Smith was a close friend of Goreleigh and served as executor of his estate. Many estate records are included in this series.
  Also of note is a scrapbook put together for Goreleigh's 70th birthday in 1972. The scrapbook contains notes and artwork by fellow artists and students, including drawings by Romare Bearden and Hughie Lee-Smith. Artwork consists of drawings, watercolors, and prints, some of which are portraits of Goreleigh. Also found are photographs of Goreleigh dating back to the 1940s.
  - Letters and Greeting Cards, circa 1973-1984 (Box 32, Folder 6-7)
  - Eyeglasses, 1986 (Box 32, Folder 8)
  - Social Security Card, undated (Box 32, Folder 9)
  - Marriage Service, 1948 (Box 32, Folder 10)
  - Certificate, 1966 (Box 32, Folder 11)
    Oversized material housed in Box 36.
  - Obituary for T. Estelle Goreleigh, 1965 (Box 32, Folder 12)
  - Travel Wallet and Passport, 1935 (Box 32, Folder 13)
  - Consignment Agreement, 1982-1983 (Box 32, Folder 14)
  - Course Syllabus, circa 1970s; 1942 (Box 32, Folder 15)
  - Notes, undated (Box 32, Folder 16)
  - Essay by Rex Goreleigh, "Discussion of a Major Character, a Subordinate Character, and an Author", 1975 (Box 32, Folder 17)
  - Wayne Hedgepeth, "The Description of a Painting 'Spring Pruning' Created by Mr. Rex Goreleigh", 1976 (Box 32, Folder 18)
  - Power of Attorney Agreement, 1982 (Box 32, Folder 19)
  - Rex Goreleigh "Support Group", 1984-1986 (Box 32, Folder 20)
  - Financial and Insurance Records, circa 1980s (Box 32, Folder 21)
  - Last Will and Testament, 1986 (Box 32, Folder 22)
  - Eulogy and Tributes to Rex Goreleigh, 1987 (Box 32, Folder 23)
  - Guest Book, 1987 (Box 32, Folder 24)
  - Estate Records, 1985-1991 (Box 32, Folder 25-29)
  - Printed Material, 1940s-1994 (Box 32, Folder 30-32)
  - Printed Material, circa 1940s-1987 (Box 33, Folder 1)
  - Photographs, circa 1950s-1980s (Box 33, Folder 2-6)
  - Slides, circa 1960s-1970s (Box 33, Folder 7-8)
  - Artwork, 1973 (Box 33, Folder 9)
  - Scrapbook, 1940s-1970s (Box 36)
  - Oversized Certificate, 1966 (Box 36)
    Oversized material from Box 32, Folder 11.
  - Oversized Artwork, 1973 (Box 36)
    Oversized material from Box 33, Folder 9.